（改编自艾萨克阿西莫夫的小说）
若问历史学家 “人类最伟大的发明是什么 ”
Ask a historian, "What was mankind's greatest invention?"
火 车轮 刀剑
Fire? The wheel? The sword?
我会说是历史本身
I would argue it's history itself.
历史不是一种事实
History isn't fact.
而是一种故事 精心策划和塑造的故事
It's narrative, one carefully curated and shaped.
在合适的人笔下
Under the pen strokes of the right scribe,
恶棍能变成英雄
a villain becomes a hero,
谎言能变成真理
a lie becomes the truth.
-爸爸 -怎么了
-Daddy? -Yeah?
-我们来自哪里  -川陀
-Where did we come from? -Trantor.
不 在那之前
No, before that.
人类在哪里诞生
Where did people come from in the beginning?
有许多不同的理论
There are lots of different theories.
大部分认为人类最初 居住在一个单一星球系统
Most of them say that humans originally inhabited a single planetary system.
只有一个
Only one?
我们甚至不知道是哪一个星球 天狼星 南门二星
And we don't even know which. Sirius, Alpha Centauri…
有人认为我们来自一个叫地球的地方
Some people think that we came from some place called Earth.
过来…
Come here. Come.
所以我们所知的一切人类
So, everyone we know about,
都来自同一个地方吗  包括安纳克里昂人和狄斯比斯人
they also came from the same place? Anacreons and Thespins too?
也包括安纳克里昂人和狄斯比斯人 没错
Anacreons and Thespins too, yeah.
那他们为什么恨我们
Then how can they hate us?
人类是复杂的 塞
Being human is complicated, Sal.
我们有共同的起源 也有一些相同的传说
We share a common origin and some of the same myths.
但我们被大脑所控制
But we're governed by this.
大脑赋予我们一切理性思考的能力
In here is all the capacity for rational thinking,
但与此同时 感性情感也存在于大脑中
but it's sharing skull space with our emotions.
有时感性的声音大过理性
And sometimes emotions shout louder than logic.
有些人的感性令他们坚信 帝国对他们不公正
And somebody's emotions got real insistent that the Empire were doing them wrong.
所以他们炸毁星桥
So they blew up the Star Bridge.
是
Yeah.
暴力是无能者最后的庇护所
Violence is the last refuge of the incompetent.
所以他们和我们完全不同 对吗
So, they're not like us at all then, right?
你小脑袋里感性的声音也很大呢
It gets loud up inside here too, doesn't it?
应该是吧
I guess it does.
过来…
Come here. Come here.
塞 问题是
Here's the thing, Sal.
星桥被炸毁时 数百万人死去
Millions of people died when that Star Bridge came down.
之后大帝又杀死了数百万的 安纳克里昂人和狄斯比斯人
And the Empire killed many millions more on Anacreon and Thespis.
所以到底谁赢了呢
And who won?
-没有人赢  -没有人赢
-Nobody? -Nobody.
就是那时我们明白了 帝国的灭亡和文明的丧失不可避免
And that's how we know that the fall is bound to happen.
过往的行为是预测未来表现的最佳指标
Past behavior is the best predictor of future performance.
塞佛哈定
Salvor Hardin…
我们在跃迁
We're jumping.
路易斯
Lewis?
路易斯 你在哪里
Lewis, where are you?
端点星
Terminus?
我们回家了
We're home.
我们跃迁回家了
We jumped back home.
路易斯
Lewis?
该死的
Damn it.
你救了我们
You saved us.
你的心愿护送我们回家了
You wished us home.
谢谢你
Thank you.
端点星指挥部 我是塞佛哈定 在帝国无敌战舰上
Terminus Control, this is Salvor Hardin, on board the imperial warship Invictus.
是否收到
Do you read me?
端点星指挥部 是否收到
Terminus Control, do you read me?
我是塞佛哈定
This is Salvor Hardin.
有人能听见吗
Can anybody hear me?
我是塞佛哈定 呼叫狄斯比斯骑兵
This is Salvor Hardin calling the Thespin lancers.
无敌战舰跃迁了 你们的飞船被带入我们的量子尾波
The Invictus jumped and we've dragged your ships into our quantum wake.
我们正在环绕端点星轨道飞行
We're in orbit around Terminus.
如果你能听见 我不知道 如何阻止飞船再次跃迁
If you can hear me, I have no idea how to stop this ship from jumping again.
也许一小时后会跃迁 也许是几天
It could be an hour from now. It could be days.
我想我被困在这里了 除非…
I figure I'm stuck here, unless…
乞丐号
The Beggar.
你怎么回家
How do you get home?
给我解释一下详细路线
Take me through your route.
这个走廊通向哪里
Where does this corridor go?
地下灌溉系统
The underground irrigation system.
但在那上方有一条路可以穿过宫殿废墟
But there's a path above it you could take through the old palace ruins.
最后你会来到仆从的出口 就在宫殿大门附近
You end up at the servants' exit, right next to the palace gates.
所以如果我从这里出去
So, if I could exit here…
超循环站就在那边
Hyperloop station's just there.
大门安检需要扫描DNA
Gate security has DNA scanners.
我需要信号消除器 隐藏我的纳米机器人 这样他们就无法追踪我
I'll need the signal damper. For my nanobots. So they can't track me.
我想我可以给你弄一个
I think I can get you one.
我不想死在这里
I don't wanna die in this place.
你不会的
You won't.
我不能保证一切会顺利
I can't promise it'll all go right.
我只能保证我不会是出错的原因
All I can promise is I won't be the part that goes wrong.
我得走了 黄昏兄弟在…
I have to go. Brother Dusk is--
克里昂
Cleon--
我真希望你不叫这个名字 拥有只属于你的名字
I wish you had another name. One that was just yours.
明天你可以为我起一个
Tomorrow you can give me one.
把信号消除器带给我 我们在另一边见
Get me that signal damper, and I'll see you on the other side.
对不起 黄昏兄弟 我刚才…
My apologies, Brother Dusk. I was--
我明白 年轻人的时间概念和我不同
I understand. Time flows differently when you're young.
我想和你说一件事
I want to share something with you.
你知道 这是我的工作地点
This is my workplace, as you know.
黄昏最重要的任务之一 是以画面记录我们的历史
The signature task of Dusk is to record our visual history.
机器人战争的结束
The end of the Robot Wars.
黄金马之叛乱
The Golden Horse Rebellion.
每当我们王朝来到了变革点
Each moment an inflection point for our dynasty,
星系的命运似乎都岌岌可危
when the fate of the galaxy seemed to be hanging in the balance.
就像这一时刻
As it did here…
我因为蛮族的野蛮之举而惩罚他们的世界
when I chastened the barbarian worlds for their acts of savagery.
在作画的时候
And even while I was painting it,
我心里想着我们作为历史的谱写者 将如何被描述
I was conscious of how we, as its authors, would be represented.
聪明的艺术家以作品表达论点
A clever artist provides commentary with his work.
即使是色彩选择这么简单的事
Even something as simple as a choice of color
也能传递隐含的意义
can convey a hidden meaning.
有时历史性的时刻并不明显
And sometimes the moment's not so obvious.
有时它会被我们忽略
Sometimes it slips past us,
你一直没有意识到它 直到那一刻过去
and you don't even realize it until it is past,
直到你第一次出现在墙上
until your debut on the wall is upon you.
我将你画进了我们的画谱
I've painted you into our legacy.
我们的狩猎
Our hunt.
你看到你击中的那三只基力猛龙了吗
Do you see the three ghillie raptors you shot?
当然
Of course.
我曾梦想有一天 我能做些丰功伟绩
I've dreamed of one day doing something,
足以让我有资格出现在这壁画里
anything, worthy enough to be included in this mural.
我不知道为何这一小事会…
I don't know why this small feat is…
我感到很荣幸 谢谢你
I'm honored. Thank you.
我本就知道你具有克里昂一世的伟大品质
I knew you had the greatness of Cleon I in you.
但在我们狩猎期间
But during our hunt,
我才意识到你还有其他品质
I realized there was something else inside you as well.
我先走了 你可以独自回顾 属于你的光辉时刻
I'll leave you to reflect on your own glorious moment.
不用急
Take your time.
欣赏微妙细腻的笔触吧
Appreciate the subtleties.
我们选择让后代知道什么 对他们隐瞒什么
What we choose to tell our children and what we censor.
突出什么 简化什么
What we illuminate and what we gloss over.
历史是一种不断做加减法的行为
History as an act of addition and subtraction.
大帝 请你去元帝塔
Empire, you're needed in the Principium Tower.
不行 我有事
I can't. I'm busy.
这是黄昏兄弟的要求
Brother Dusk insists.
我身体有恙
I'm indisposed.
等我一分钟 我会去的 只需一分钟
I need a minute alone, and I'll come along. One minute.
你知道 我也是大帝
I am also Empire, you know.
是 大帝
Yes, Empire.
但我们都服侍帝国
But we both serve.
我忘了东西 我需要回去
I forgot something. I need to go back.
不急
It can wait.
封锁入口
Lock down the entrance.
不许任何人进出
Don't let anyone in or out.
有条路可以穿过宫殿废墟
There's a path you can take through the palace ruins.
最后你会来到仆从的出口 就在宫殿大门附近
You end up at the servants' exit, right next to the palace gates.
这条路通向地下灌溉系统
This route takes you to the underground irrigation system.
超循环站就在那边
Hyperloop station's just there.
分散开来
Spread out.
警告 水循环即将开始
Warning. Water cycling imminent.
我的天啊 这个跳跃的距离也太远了
Four moons, that's a long jump.
跳吧
Go.
乞丐号 快给我醒来
Beggar, wake the hell up.
欢迎上船 哈定船长
Welcome aboard, Captain Hardin.
打扰一下
Excuse me?
这是帝国护身环 能换你的外套吗
It's an imperial aura. For your jacket?
你能告诉我怎么去33层的德司尼安区吗
Can you tell me how to get to the Desnian Sector on level 33?
乘坐钴线向下 然后转乘埃利环线
Take the Cobalt Line down, then transfer to Ery Loop.
向核心区走
You wanna head inner core.
乞丐号 开启连接端点星的频道
Beggar, open a channel to Terminus Control.
通讯频道已开启
Communications channel open.
端点星指挥部 我是塞佛哈定 请回答
Terminus Control, this is Salvor Hardin. Come in.
见鬼了
Damn it.
乞丐号 扫描所有波幅 寻找任何可连接的通讯点
Beggar, scan all frequencies. Find me anyone on comms.
扫描中
Scanning.
未发现端点星地表上 存在任何运行的通讯站
No active comms detected on the surface of Terminus.
你找到了吗
You found someone?
警告 异常碎屑 可能位于撞击轨道
Caution. Anomalous debris on potential intercept trajectory.
危险级别低
Threat level low.
那是什么鬼东西
What the hell is that?
警告 异常碎屑 确认位于撞击轨道
Alert. Anomalous debris on confirmed intercept trajectory.
危险级别中
Threat level moderate.
我需要火炮 火炮在哪里
I need guns. Where are the guns?
乞丐号 说明火炮位置
Beggar, show me the guns.
警告 异常碎屑即将撞击
Warning. Anomalous debris object impact imminent.
危险级别极高 警告
Threat level severe. Warning.
锁定目标
Target locked.
宝贝 是你吗
Babe? Babe, are you there?
雨果 是你吗
Hugo, is that you?
我们的计划成功了 塞
Our plan worked, Sal.
你是怎么从星带过来的
How'd you get here from the Belt?
主要靠运气
Luck, mostly.
我联络上狄斯比斯指挥部 我搭上了其中一艘骑兵飞船的副驾
I made contact with Thespin Command. I rode shotgun on one of the lancers.
我发现无敌战舰即将跃迁
And then I could see the Invictus was about to jump,
所以我拿了一个麻醉棍 让自己晕了过去 以进行跃迁
so I grabbed a sedation stick and knocked myself out for the jump.
提醒其他人也这么做
Warned the rest of my people to do the same.
醒来就听见你美妙的声音
And I woke up to the dulcet tones of your voice.
但我不明白为什么你这么快醒来
But I don't understand how you woke up so quickly.
我并没有真的睡过去 就和穹窿一样
I never went to sleep. It's like the Vault.
我无法解释原因 但跃迁对我没有影响
I can't explain how or why, but the jump just didn't affect me.
所以你带我们回到端点星了
So you got us back to Terminus?
不 那是路易斯的功劳 他为了送我们回家牺牲了自己
No, that was Lewis. He died to get us back.
基地没有回应
And the Foundation's not responding?
没有任何人回应
No one is,
就连法拉留下的安纳克里昂人都没有
not even the Anacreons Phara left behind.
是空域的作用
It's the null field.
我能感觉到 雨果
I can feel it, Hugo.
它变得更大 更响了
It's… even bigger. It's… louder.
就像在慢慢包裹整个星球
It's like it's enveloped the whole planet.
我必须阻止它
I have to stop it.
你疯了吗
Are you crazy?
要是他们都死了呢
What if they're all dead down there?
不如我们直接离开 就现在
What if we just left? Right now.
我们可以去红廊避难
We'll make a run for the Red Corridor.
我可以带你看艾琳娜四号星 长庚星
I'll show you Irina Four, I'll show you Hesperus--
我不能这么做 雨果
I can't, Hugo.
如果这场危机并没有解决方案呢
What if there is no solution to this crisis?
如果谢顿的预测是错的呢
What if Seldon got it wrong?
我必须坚持到最后 雨果
I have to see this through, Hugo.
我必须挽回局面
I have to fix this.
你希望我怎么做
What do you want me to do?
无敌战舰会再次跃迁 除非你的人能够关闭它的驱动器
The Invictus is gonna jump again unless your people can disable its drives.
那就让它跃迁 让它带走法拉 我们再也不用见它了
Then let it jump. Let it take Phara. It'll be out of our lives forever.
不
No.
基地需要这艘飞船
The Foundation needs that ship.
那是我们终结危机的办法
It's the way we end the crisis.
-我无法告诉你如何… -我只是有种感觉
-I can't tell you how… -I just have a feeling.
你说过你对我坚信不疑
You said you have absolute faith in me.
你的信念动摇了吗
You still believe that?
如果现在改变主意 我是不是有点过分
Be kind of a dick if I changed my mind now, wouldn't I?
我们在目的地见
I'll see you on the other side.
我爱你
I love you.
我也爱你
Me too.
你人生的每一分 每一秒 都在别人的注视下度过
You've lived every moment of your life with people watching you.
疤痕区不是这样
The Scar's different.
你可以在那里混入人群
You can lose yourself in it.
对于帝国而言 疤痕区代表着失败
For Empire, the Scar represents a failure.
对于川陀的其他人来说 它是一次机会
For the rest of Trantor, it represents an opportunity.
数百年来的第一次
For the first time in centuries,
我们可以抬头看见真的云朵和星辰
we can look up and see real clouds, real stars,
而不是为了让我们安于现状的 服务器运行模拟天空
not a simulation run by servers designed to keep us complacent.
我居住在第33层的德司尼安区
I live on level 33, in the Desnian Sector.
老特尔夏做的风味马尔卡饼 是整个星球最美味的
Old Tertia makes the best spiced malkas on the planet.
这是我称之为家的走廊
This is the corridor I take home.
和你的宫殿是两个天地
It's nothing like your palace.
这里吵闹喧嚣 熙熙攘攘
It's chaotic. It's crowded.
但这里是鲜活的
But it's alive.
它正等着你
And it's waiting for you.
我不能再等了
I couldn't wait.
你没有戴护身环
You're not wearing your aura.
我用它换了这件外套 以免别人认出我
I traded it for this, so I wouldn't be recognized.
换外套这招挺聪明的
The jacket's smart.
现在我们可以烧了它
Now we can burn it.
我们得移除我的纳米机器人 以防他们在追踪
We need to get my nanobots removed in case they're tracking me. I…
我也许根本不该留在这里
I probably shouldn't even stay here.
没事 我有信号消除器
It's okay. I got the signal damper.
它可以隐藏你的踪迹 直到我们…
That'll cover you until we can arrange to…
嘿
Hey.
最难的部分已经结束了
The hardest part's over.
你逃离了他们
You got away from them.
你来到这里了
You're here.
但是 说真的
But, truthfully…
你身上的味道仍然很难闻
you still smell terrible.
不如你洗个澡吧
Why don't you shower?
嘿 我在想给自己起个新名字
Hey, I was thinking about a new name for me.
阿祖拉
Azura?
那是用来做什么的
What is that for?
塞佛说引擎室在那边
According to Salvor, the engine room is that way.
我们有大约33个小时来关闭跃迁驱动器
We've got about thirty-three hours to disable the jumpdrives.
这里发生了什么
What happened here?
一个漫长而可怕的故事 没有人活下来讲述它
A long and terrible story that no one's alive to tell…
安纳克里昂人在哪
Anacreons, where?
舰桥那边 塞佛把他们绑在那里了
The bridge. Salvor has them tied up in there.
安全
All clear.
一位智者曾说
A wise man once said,
“没有历史的民族就如无根的树”
"A people without history is like a tree without roots."
那位智者的历史缺失了什么
What's missing from the wise man's history?
是从何时开始 故事代替了事实
When did story replace record?
当所有事实都不再可信
When all the facts fall short of believability,
幻想反而有一种令人安心的真实感
fantasy feels reassuringly solid.
而由于这是我的历史
And since this is my history,
我可以决定删减哪一部分
I get to decide which parts have been subtracted,
增添哪一部分
which have been added.
乔德
Jord?
妈妈…
Mom? Mom?
妈妈…醒醒 是我
Mom. Mom, wake up, it's me.
你能理解它吗
Can you make anything of it?
好吧 我自己破解
Fine. I'll figure it out myself.
松开拳头 塞佛
Open your fists, Salvor.
来吧
Come on.
你能理解它吗
Can you make anything of it?
塞佛 如果你是计划的一部分
Salvor, if you were part of the Plan,
那我会更容易相信这一切
it would make it a lot easier for me to believe in all this.
你用了多久
How long did it take you…
激活元光体
to trigger the Prime Radiant?
我第二次尝试时成功了
Got it on the second try.
历史是终极武器 因为它能驾驭时间
History is the ultimate weapon, because it harnesses time itself.
正确地利用时间 过去就能改变现在
Used correctly, the past can alter the present.
还有哪种发明能够做到这点
What other invention can do that?
塞佛
Salvor?
妈妈
Mom?
-我还以为再也见不到你了 -我也是
-I thought I'd never see you again. -Me too.
空域停止了
The null field, it's stopped.
是你做的吗
Did you do this?
那是门吗
Is that a door?
好像是的
I think so.
那现在怎么办
So, what now?
现在是结束的时候
Now is where it ends.
你找到猎手了吗
Did you find the Huntress?
我们搜寻了整艘飞船
We searched the entire ship.
没有她的踪迹
No sign of her.
除了这个
Except this.
那么我们尽快赶到端点星
Then we get down to Terminus as fast as possible.
黑曜岩号 开启与长石砂岩号 和片麻岩号的通讯频道
Obsidian, open a channel to Arkose and Gneiss.
通讯频道已开启
Communications channel open.
这是狄斯比斯指挥部
This is Thespin Command.
所有骑兵立即前往星球
I want all lancers planet-side immediately.
飞船由你们中的谁指挥
Which one of you is this ship slave to?
让飞船听命于法拉柯恩 否则你也会死
Slave this ship to Phara Keaen, or you die too.
长石砂岩号 启动规程 飞船转移 法拉柯恩
Arkose, invoke protocol. Ship transfer, Phara Keaen.
心率增加
Heart rate's rising.
如果达到120次 那么机器人会进入紧急模式
If it gets to 120, then the bots go into crisis mode.
我会增加抑制剂量
I'll increase the inhibitors.
脉搏渐渐平稳
Pulse is stabilizing.
开始传输吧
Start the transfer now.
我们正将你的纳米机器人传输至我的血液
We're transferring your nanobots into my blood.
这是你想要的 对吧
That's what you wanted, isn't it?
移除它们
To have them removed?
你是什么人
Who are you?
黎明的克隆人 显而易见
A Dawn clone, obviously.
在外表上与你一模一样
Superficially identical to you.
但你是如何…
But how are you…
来到这里 而不是漂浮在水族箱里
Here? Instead of floating in an aquarium?
我们的人成功将克里昂一世的部分DNA 从宫殿中偷出来
Our people managed to smuggle some of Cleon I's DNA out of the palace.
为了这一天 我们已经努力了数十年
We've been working towards this day for decades.
你出乎我们的意料 我们原计划明天才帮你逃出来
You surprised us. We'd planned to have you escape tomorrow.
阿祖拉在哪里
Where's Azura?
这一切都是陷阱
This was all a trap.
你怎么能这样对我
How could you do this to me?
你
You?
这关乎星系的其他人
This is about the rest of the galaxy,
所有被帝国压迫的星球和人民
all the planets and people who've been crushed under the Empire's heel.
这不是他的错
It's not his fault.
他是在这种环境下长大的
It's how he was raised.
一直以来 他和他的兄弟们总是听人们说
He and his brothers have always been told
他们是不会灭的明光 永不断裂的锁链
they are the light that never dims, an unbroken chain.
他们那小天地的宫墙隔离了残酷的现实
Reality just doesn't penetrate their little terrarium.
我不知道你要如何忍受
I don't know how you're gonna stomach it.
我不会有事
I'll be fine.
我已经练习扮演这个角色太久了
I've been practicing my role long enough,
尚在成长的小暴君
the cloistered little tyrant in the making…
身上笼罩着一种微弱的 自怜又自负的高冷气质
projecting that subtle air of self-pitying, arrogant indifference.
练习 你在说什么
Practicing? What are you talking about?
“练习 你在说什么 ”
"Practicing? What are you talking about?"
我是你的替身 黎明
I'm your understudy, Dawn.
现在我该登上舞台了
And now it's time for me to take center stage.
我会回到宫殿
I'm going to go back to the palace,
成为你
and I'm gonna be you.
他们会杀了你 他们知道我不一样
They'll just kill you then. They know I'm different.
对 可是…
Right, but…
我与你不同
I'm not.
我并非色盲 我不是左撇子
I'm not color-blind. I'm not left-handed.
在基因上 我与克里昂一世一模一样
I'm genetically identical to Cleon I.
我可以证明
And I can prove it.
我不懂
I don't understand.
怎么可能你与一世一模一样而我却不是
How can you be identical to the first, and I'm not?
技术术语是“磁性纳米粒子转染”
"Magnetic nanoparticle transfection" is the technical term.
具体情况太过复杂 我也不懂
It's all a little over my head,
但是简单说来 在克隆你之后 他们修改了你的DNA
but, basically, they altered your DNA after the fact.
正如我说的 在你我出生之前 这一切都已计划好了
Like I said, this has been planned since before you or I took our first breath.
我们的人明白必须让你离开宫殿
Our people knew they had to get you out of the palace,
但他们不能直接绑走你
but they couldn't just take you.
那样太危险
That would've been too risky.
他们必须让你自己选择离开
They had to make it so you'd choose to leave.
你需要一个逃走的动机 还有比生存更好的动机吗
You needed a motive to run. And what better motive than survival?
大帝 是我们让你变得不一样
We're the ones who made you different, Empire.
从某种意义而言 你其实很幸运
In a certain way, you're lucky too.
一脉相承的王朝是人类的耻辱
The Genetic Dynasty's an affront to humanity,
而你已不是其中的一部分
and you're no longer part of it.
你从来都不是
You never really were.
传输完成了
The transfer's complete.
从头到尾 你没有任何选择
You had no choice in any of this…
但我们仍然感谢你
but thank you just the same.
扶他起来
Get him up.
你们要对我做什么
What are you gonna do to me?
你觉得呢 克里昂
What do you think, Cleon?
阿祖拉…这边
Azura. Azura, this way.
大帝
Empire.
黄昏兄弟 我真感激
Brother Dusk! I am so grateful.
彻底审查所有死者的记忆
I want a full memory audit of all the dead.
这女孩呢
And the girl?
这女孩 是
The girl. Yes.
演技令人赞叹
Quite a performance.
作为观众欣赏这场表演 很荣幸
It was a pleasure to observe it,
虽然只能蒙骗年轻人和傻子
tailored though it was to the young and foolish.
你该不会认为 我们会任由这个无人机离开宫殿
You didn't really think we'd let this drone leave the palace
而不通知我们吧
without alerting us, did you?
亲爱的 我们一路跟随你们 令人激动的旅程 回到这里
We followed your whole enticing travelogue home, my dear.
你放他走 从而跟着他找到我们
You let him get away so he would lead you to us.
捆缚她
Shroud her.
你已经得到你想要的了
You got what you wanted then.
永远别以为你理解我想要什么
Never presume to understand what I want.
你愚蠢 天真 易受骗
You are stupid, naive, gullible.
我在你这个年纪也是如此
So was I at your age.
这些是可以原谅的
And these things are forgivable.
但你的不同之处
But the matter of your… difference,
这个问题则复杂得多
that's rather more complicated.
但你一定也听到他们的话了
But you must've heard them.
我是受害者 我们都是
I'm a victim. We all are.
是
Yes.
这让你变成我们脆弱的象征
And that makes you the embodiment of our vulnerability,
一个令人不快的标识 提醒着我们
an ugly reminder of the knife-edge
一脉相承的王朝之根基如此脆弱
upon which our Genetic Dynasty is balanced.
我们有何理由会想再看到你的脸
By what logic would we want to look on your face ever again?
我的脸
My face?
我的脸就是你的脸
My face is your face.
别管逻辑 试着换位思考一下吧
Forget logic. Try empathy.
等等…
Wait, wait, wait.
当然不是你说了算 而取决于白昼
Surely it's not up to you. It's up to Day.
是的
True.
白昼兄弟很快将回家
Brother Day will be home soon.
你可以向他求情
You can plead your case to him.
我猜他在经历了少女星的事之后 应该是心烦意乱的
I doubt his experience on the Maiden has made him serene.
守卫者 你安全返回了
Warden, you made it back!
你们两人离我远点
Keep your distance, you two.
但大家都醒了 已经结束了
But everyone's waking up. It's over.
还没结束
It's not over.
塞佛 等等 别过去
Salvor, wait. Don't go in there.
我必须这么做 妈妈
I have to, Mom.
别去 止步
You will not! Step away.
你说过这不是陷阱 你不知道这是什么情况
You said this wasn't a trick, that you didn't know what this was.
我们确实不知道
We don't.
但你的女儿却让它停止了 你要如何解释
And yet your daughter has tamed it. How do you explain that?
抱歉 塞 我试图说服他们别着陆
Sorry, Sal. I tried to talk 'em out of landing.
不 这是合理的
No, this makes sense.
我应该在这里 所有事件汇合为一场危机
This is where I'm supposed to be. Everything converging in a single crisis.
我们的猎手在哪
Where is our Huntress?
她失去了对无敌战舰的控制
She lost control of the Invictus.
你们殉道 摧毁川陀的计划已经失败了
Your plans for martyrdom, for Trantor, they're done.
罗文
Rowan?
维伊尔德诸神已经背弃我们
The Weald Gods have forsaken us.
噢 真该死
Oh, hammered shit.
这画面真美
Well, isn't this a pretty picture?
新旧敌人齐聚一堂
Enemies old and new, conveniently gathered in one place.
放下武器 给他松绑
Drop your weapons and unbind him.
你 守卫者 别想着抛你那枚硬币
And you, Warden, don't even think about flashing that coin of yours.
法拉 很高兴你还活着 真的
I'm glad you're alive, Phara, truly.
请你也听我说
I need you to hear this.
我最不想听的就是你的话
Last thing I'm interested in hearing is more words from you.
法拉 拜托了 跃迁会导致精神错乱 你的思维不理性
Phara, please. The jump induces psychosis. You're not thinking straight.
我的思维没问题
I'm thinking just fine.
瞄准目标的能力也是
Also aiming.
听着 如果你不喜欢我接下来的话
Look, if you don't like what I have to say,
我说完话 你可以杀了我 你可以杀死所有人
you can kill me when I'm done. You can kill all of us.
我会的
I will.
那艘飞船
That ship…
是你们族群将取得的最强大武器
is the most powerful weapon your people will ever get their hands on.
如果是这样 为何摧毁它
If that's the case, why destroy it?
-为何不利用它  -如何利用
-Why not use it for leverage? -How?
我们团结起来 三个世界的人齐心协力
We band together, all three worlds.
别再移动
Stop moving!
我们可以共享无敌战舰
We can share the Invictus.
我们可以合作修好它
We can repair it, together.
我们只需要让理性的声音比感性更响亮
All we have to do is let our logic speak louder than our emotions.
法拉 停下
Phara, stop.
你要与你们的猎手为敌
You would take up arms against your own Huntress?
狩猎行动结束了 法拉
The hunt is over, Phara.
法拉 停下
Phara, stop!
-瞄准 -弗里斯通 等等
-Take aim! -Freestone, wait!
她死了 放下武器吧
She's gone. Drop it.
眼前的景象令人鼓舞啊
Well, this is encouraging.
安纳克里昂人 狄斯比斯人和端点星人
Anacreons, Thespins, and Termini.
见到大家齐聚在此 我看到了希望
Seeing you all gathered here gives me hope…
也许我们真的能取得成功
we might actually pull this off.
字幕翻译：易晗
前情提要
Previously on Foundation…
我给你带了个东西 色彩校正镜
I've brought you something. Color-correction 'hesives.
这样你就能看到红绿了
So you can see red and green.
如果他们知道我的与众不同 那会是我在世上的最后一天
If they ever learn how different I am, it'll be my last day.
射死六只 这一定能让黄昏兄弟印象深刻
Six kills. Brother Dusk will be impressed.
把这些扔进树丛 我射死了三只
Throw these in the bushes. I killed three.
法拉想让我们帮她取得战舰的掌控权
Phara wants us to help her take control of the ship.
无敌战舰
The Invictus?
一个摧毁世界的杀手
A world-killer.
这些老式飞船 需要具备强大处理能力的东西
These older ships needed something with massive processing power
来为跃迁提供导航
to navigate their jumps.
他们不得不与飞船直接相连
They had to be hardwired directly into the ships.
不做手术可以直接连接吗
Could someone jack in without the surgery?
那等于判了死刑
It would be a death sentence.